# Sharad Kumar Gupta

**LinkedIn:** https://www.linkedin.com/in/sharad-gupta-oracleconsultant/

### **Profile Summary**

#### Lead Consultant / Technical Delivery Lead

17.10 years of progressive experience in IT consulting, Oracle Cloud HCM, exhibiting excellence in solution design, managing support projects, collaborating with project teams, interfacing with clients and deploying technology to build successful solutions for clients, Delivery Management, Resourcing, Application Solution Design & Development, Application Support, Client Management and overall Project Management & Coordination across Retail, Manufacturing, United Nations, Logistics, Airways, IT, Educational University, Government Organization.

#### **Key Highlights:**

- Solution Architecture:
  - o Proficient in designing and modifying technology architectures to address complex organizational challenges.
- Project Management:
  - Successfully led Oracle HRMS/HCM support, and enhancement projects.
- Functional & Technical Competence:
  - o Well-versed with Functional domain knowledge of Core HR, Absence, SSHR, and Integration.
  - Well-versed in technologies such as HDL/HSDL, BIP Report, Rest APIs, OTBI, Personalization, Fast Formula,
     Embedded reports, Exposure to HCM Extract, Roles based security, Workflow Approval, Alert composer etc.

#### **Professional Achievements:**

- Conducted analysis of applications, identifying system improvement plans (SIPs) to enhance stability and reduce support issues and costs.
- Ensured timely resolution of customer queries in adherence to SLAs.
- Fostered effective collaboration with Shared Services, Core HR, and non-ERP HR departments.
- Results-oriented professional with good experience in Oracle ERP implementation as well as other technologies.
- Versatile and multi-skilled with ability to manage multiple responsibilities simultaneously, an effective communicator with strong analytical & critical problem solving.
- Proficient in managing a team of functional and technical staff members and leads a project's development efforts for all areas within product development by establishing development objectives and project timelines, determining, and obtaining resources, assigning work, monitoring progress and results, and providing technical leadership.
- Collaborated with Pre-Sales teams on new proposals (RFPs), demonstrating a deep understanding of client needs.

#### **Education**

 Bachelor of Technology in Electronics and Communications Engg, University, Kurukshetra University Kurukshetra, Haryana, India, 2006

## **Certifications / Other Course / Achievements**

- Scrum Alliance Certified Scrum Master 2023
- Oracle Cloud Infrastructure 2023 Certified Application Integration Professional
- Oracle HCM Business Process Certified Foundations Associates Re 2\_2023
- Oracle Cloud Platform Application Integration 2021 Certified Specialist (120-1042- 21)
- Information Security Awareness.
- Digital Awareness Program.
- Accolade EAS Team Aspiration Award FY 16-17 [Q1]
- Accolade with Customer Centricity (Leader) FY21 [H2]
- Mentor a batch of 50 New Joiner

## **Core Competencies**

Expertise in Oracle HRMS / Oracle Cloud HCM and have the specialization in Core HR, SSHR, and Integration.

- IT Project Management, Progress monitoring, Team Management, Client & Relationship Management
  - Hands-on experience in leading all stages of software development life-cycle Development, delivery.
  - Managing teams for projects entailing design, implementation & deployment; technical expertise in all the phases of analysis, design, development and testing of various solutions
  - Hands-on experience in Functional Setup on Oracle HRMS/HCM (CORE HR, SSHR, Absence) Module.
  - Training & Development Knowledge Transfer.
- Work closely with clients to define and design their technology footprint as part of the implementation roadmap.

#### • Integration Expertise:

 Define standard operating procedures for seamless integration between Oracle and non-Oracle technologies.

## • Technical Solution Design:

 Lead Technical Solution Design workshops, creating strategies for conversions, integrations, reports, and extensions for large and complex Oracle Fusion implementations.

#### Advisory Role:

o Provide technical advice on solutions, architecture designs, strategy, and implementation best practices.

## • Project Planning and Execution:

Plan deliverable timelines and allocate resources for the project scope, timeline, and execution.

#### Team Management:

- Strong leadership skills in leading and managing teams.
- Ability to inspire and motivate team members, foster collaboration, and drive team performance to achieve project objectives.

#### • Client Relationship Management:

- Exceptional ability to build and maintain strong relationships with clients.
- Skilled in understanding client needs, providing effective solutions, and ensuring client satisfaction.
- o Proficient in conducting client presentations and managing client expectations.

## • Time Management:

- Excellent time management skills to prioritize tasks, meet deadlines, and manage multiple projects simultaneously.
- o Ability to effectively allocate resources and optimize productivity.

### • Solution Design and Estimation:

- Expertise in designing and estimating solutions for complex business problems.
- Ability to analyze requirements, propose innovative solutions, and provide effort estimations.

## • Cross-Functional Supervision:

- o Ability to oversee and coordinate activities across different functional areas within an organization.
- o Skilled in aligning cross-functional teams, resolving conflicts, and ensuring smooth collaboration.

## **Work Experience**

Highstreet IT Solution as Lead Consultant /Technical Delivery Le	ad Jan'2022 – Sep'2024
Client	Period
Johnson City, Tennessee, United States	Apr 2022 - Aug 2024
City of Bakersfield, U.S.	May 2023- Apr 2024
Syracuse City School District, U.S.	Aug 2023 - May 2024
Springfield Public Schools, New Jersey, U.S.	Dec 2023 - June 2024
Chicago Park District, Chicago, United States	Feb 2024 - June 2024
Brazos County, Texas, U.S.	Jun 2023 - Jan 2024
City Of Hollywood, Florida, U.S.	Jan 2022 - Mar 2023
City Of Greeley, Colorado, U.S.	Jan 2022 - May 2022

#### **Key Accountabilities**

- Conducted thorough requirement gathering sessions with clients to understand their needs.
- Prepared detailed requirement documents, ensuring clarity and alignment with project goals.
- Created fitment documents to map client requirements to product features.
- Conducted product demos for clients, showcasing how our solution met their needs.
- Conduct walkthrough of Assessment Document on Oracle Quarterly released feature for HCM.
- Developed Report for Annual Secretary of Board Report to maintained fund allocation to the Springfield schools.
- Worker Data Conversion from third party application (Munis) to Oracle cloud using Bridges as Integration.
- Generated project health reports and weekly status updates.
- Worked on BIP (Business Intelligence Publisher) and OTBI (Oracle Transactional Business Intelligence) reporting.
- Worked on HCM Data Loader to upload Element Entry for an employee.
- Customization of seeded report template.
- Using Highstreet Bridges as Integration Tool and using REST API for data migration from third party to Oracle Fusion cloud to upload timecard into OTL.
- Assigned Roles based security to the user to see respective data.
- Implemented system improvements and conducted causal analyses for HR applications.
- Monitor project progress throughout project life cycle, communicate project status effectively to senior management through reports, presentations, and individual meetings.
- Build and provide direction to project teams, create and foster communication among team members.
- Identify resource needs, constraints, and inter-dependencies.
- Managing a team of technical, functional, as well as handling resource planning and staffing for teams on a broad range of Project & Support engagements, maximizing billable utilization. Managing multiple projects at a time and ensure that the quality standards for delivery are exceeded.
- Review the Issue Tracker and ensure to close the issue on define timeline.
- Wrote the Fast formula to increase the limit of compensatory leave for an employee.
- Worked on HDL to load Time Record Group Entries for employees.
- Customization of seeded Customer Statement Report.
- Developed Invoice Pending Final Approval AP Report.
- Implemented workflow approval for change location process. Created approval group hierarchy to setup the rules for approval.
- · Worked on alert composer to send notification to the supervisor on employee's ending Probation period.
- Demo on HCM Extract creation using user entity and apply filter and delivery using FTP and scheduling of the extract. And run through flow submission.
- Created the repository of the delivered task to maintain and refer the solutions.
- Created SOW for new requirements.
- Created the project scope and WBS to track project progress.
- Maintained the risk register and repository to ensure the learning from the past project deliverable.
- Manage resource handling and conflict management.

#### Zensar Technologies Ltd. Technical Specialist/Team Lead

Aug'2013 - Jan'2022

Client	Period
The Foschini Group, Cape Town, South Africa	Apr 2018 – Jan 2022
Cree Inc., Durham, North Carolina, U.S.	Sep 2017- Mar-2018
Zensar Technologies Ltd., Pune, India	Jan 2017 - Sep 2017
World Health Organization, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia	Nov 2015 – Dec 2016
Price Water House Cooper Pvt. Ltd., Kolkata, India	Oct 2014- Oct 2015
John Lewis Partnership, London, U.K.	Aug 2013- Oct 2015

## **Key Accountabilities**

- Conducted thorough requirement gathering sessions with clients to understand their needs.
- Prepared detailed requirement documents, ensuring clarity and alignment with project goals.
- Conducted product demos for clients, showcasing how our solution met their needs.

- Facilitated user training sessions to ensure smooth adoption of the system.
- Managed end-to-end project lifecycles, including planning, execution, and monitoring.
- Built end to end application for Package Calculator to calculate Tax, Net Pay for both TFG Regular and Retired Employees using OAF as UI and PLSQL and Payroll API for backend activity.
- Integration of OAF with Enterprise Content Management.
- Designed AME based on supervisor and role-based approver.
- Worked on Workflow enhancement, and EIT creation.
- Involved in code review process.
- Creation of SIT, EIT, Flex Field. Register EIT. OAF Personalization.
- Raised and Monitored SRs with Oracle and coordinating with them for final resolution.
- Provide guidance to team members for on time delivery.
- Prioritized projects and project tasks depending upon key milestones and deadline dates.

### Polaris Financial Tech. Ltd. Sr. Software Engineer / Team Lead

Jun'2012 - Jul'2013

Client	Period
Qatar Airways, Doha, Qatar	Jun 2012 – Jul 2013

#### **Key Accountabilities**

- Conducted thorough requirement gathering sessions with clients to understand their needs.
- Responsible for RICE (Reports, Interfaces and Extension) components
- Developed the interfaces for data migration between Oracle to legacy system and vice versa.
- Provided outstanding service to clients through effective communication and Project management skill and domain expertise.
- Developed Custom IT Asset Tracking System application using R12 web-based OAF Pages to track the movement of an
  asset. The process involves, from issuing of asset either to the employee or department to the returning,
  replacement, transfer and disposed of the asset.
- Involved in code review process.
- Provide guidance to team members for on time delivery.

## FLSmidth Pvt. Ltd. as Senior Consultant / Individual Contributor

Aug'2011 - Jun'2012

Client	Period
FLSmidth Private Ltd., Denmark, Copenhagen	Aug 2011 – Jul 2012

### **Key Accountabilities**

- Conducted thorough requirement gathering sessions with clients to understand their needs.
- Prepared detailed requirement documents, ensuring clarity and alignment with project goals.
- Suggest the framework solution to team and developed the web-based OAFPages.
- Facilitated user training sessions to ensure smooth adoption of the system.
- Prioritized projects and project tasks depending upon key milestones and deadline dates.

## Mahindra Satyam Computers Ltd. as Sr. Consultant

Nov'2006 - Aug'2011

Client	Period
Royal Jordanian Airline, Jordan	Sep 2010- Aug 2011
Keya Airways, Keya, Africa	Apr 2009 – Sep 2010
Qantas Airways, Sydney, Australia	Oct 2008 – Apr 2009
Logitech, Lausanne, Switzerland	Sep 2007 – Oct 2008
Cisco, San Jose, California, U.S.	Nov 2006 – Aug 2007

## **Key Accountabilities:**

• Involved in thorough requirement gathering sessions with clients to understand business needs.

- Designing the generic product with flexibility to expand the product in future.
- Drive the entire development and testing cycle of the generic product at offshore.
- Handling the delivery of Royal Jordanian Airlines UMS implementation from offshore, starting from UAT to GO LIVE, including UMS delivery plan, resource management, issues management & provide appropriate guideline to onsite team to ensure smooth go live.
- Discussion with Client and providing optimized solution and design.
- Effort Estimation, component delivery planning, Testing, Scope Change Management.
- Imparted training to User, Keys User and made them familiar with the product.
- Review the Issue and ensure to close the issue within defined SLAs.
- Prepare MD50/MD70 document as per process.
- Involved in Development, code review, testing and production migration.
- Raised and Monitored SRs with Oracle and coordinating with them for final resolution.